A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Higher Education and Research Division, Program Staff Files FA546
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Higher Education and Research Division, Program Staff Files
1954-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA546
7.17 Cubic Feet
The collection of Program Staff Files of the Higher Education and Research Division combines the files of several staff members from the Higher Education and Research Division, the International Affairs Division, and the Office of the Secretary. It spans from 1954 to 1970. Files within this collection contain background on the Broadcasters Nonprofit Satellite Service, the PAYE loan project, the Science and Engineering program, international educational grant-making files and educational issues such as desegregation, school drop-outs, and support for disadvantaged minorities. There are also research files from Corinne Kirchner in the Office of the Secretary. The provenance of this collection is unclear. It appears to have been created by combining the files of staff members within the Higher Education and Research Division with some education-related grant-making records from the International Division and the Office of the Secretary.
17 Hollinger document boxes, 1 oversize box (18 boxes total)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials Note
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Chronological files belonging to Robert H. Edwards were identified among documents originating from Dorothy V. White. These chronological files were separated and added to the Office Files of Robert H. Edwards, ACC2011/021.
Organizational History
The fostering of education has been one of the Foundation's longest and most consistent goals. Beginning in 1952 with the Fund for Adult Education and the Fund for the Advancement of Education, and continuing through the present day with the Education, Creativity and Free Expression Program, the Ford Foundation has maintained an ongoing program of educational grant-making.
The Education and the Science and Engineering Divisions were created during the 1957 fiscal year. In 1966, Education became the Education and Research Division, and Higher Education and Research was created as a program area under the umbrella of Education and Research. That same year, the decision was made to phase out the Science and Engineering program and no further Science and Engineering grants were to be made after the December 1966 meeting of the Board of Trustees. As part of a reorganization in 1979, Education and Research became a program area under the Education and Public Policy Division. During subsequent reorganization in 1981 Education and Culture became a program of the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Division.
Biographical Notes
Born in 1905, Carl Williams Borgmann graduated from the University of Colorado with a B.S. in 1927 and was awarded an M.S. in 1931. He worked in the private sector until 1938 when he returned to the University to head the University's Department of Chemical Engineering. He later held various war-related engineering positions before accepting a position as Dean of Faculties at the University of Nebraska in 1947. He left in 1952 to become president of the University of Vermont. Later, in 1958, he was appointed the Ford Foundation's Program Director of Science and Engineering. During the span of the Ford Foundation Program in Science and Engineering (1958-1966), Dr. Borgmann directed activities related to engineering education. His work largely concerned developing methods to improve educational and experimental backgrounds of university engineering faculty and the expansion and enhancement of programs for advanced graduate education. Dr. Borgmann served as Director of the Science and Engineering program until 1965, after which he held the position of Advisor on Science and Technology until 1969. He died in 1998.
Abel C. Amaya was a Program Officer in the Higher Education and Research program until 1974. An Associate Professor with the History Department at Colorado State University and the Director of the Chicano Studies Program, he took a five year leave of absence in order to serve as a Program Officer at the Ford Foundation. Dr. Amaya later served as director of El Centro Chicano at the University of Southern California from 1979 to 1999.
Peter E. de Janosi was born on June 26, 1928 in Pecs, Hungary and died on February 16, 2011. A graduate of Wesleyan University with a B.A. in 1950, he received an M.A. in 1951 and a Ph.D. in Economics from the University of Michigan in 1956. After holding the position of Senior Economist at the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey from 1956 to 1962, he was hired as a Program Officer by the Ford Foundation. He served as a Program Associate in the Economic Development and Administration until 1965, when he was promoted to Officer in Charge of Higher Education and Research, a position he held until 1976. He subsequently worked as a Program Officer in Resources and the Environment until 1980, when he left the Foundation to become Vice-President of the Russell Sage Foundation (1980-1990). He later was appointed Director of the International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis in Laxenburg, Austria (1990-1996).
Corinne Kirchner (b.1935) served in the Office of the Secretary in several capacities between 1956 and 1969, including Supervisor of Grant Analysis. In this capacity she helped prepare reports in support of Foundation research, including reports on faculty salaries, fellowships and scholarships.
Edward J. Meade Jr. was born on September 7, 1930. He attended Montclair State College and received a B.A. in Education, Business and Geography in 1954. He was subsequently awarded an M.A. in Educational Administration in 1956, and later earned an Ed.D in Education from Harvard University in 1960. Dr. Meade joined the Foundation in January 1961 as a Program Specialist in the Education Division. He was promoted to Program Assistant the next year, and in October 1963, became a Program Associate. Dr. Meade was appointed Officer in Charge of Public Education in the Division of Education and Research in January 1967. He held that position for next decade. In October 1977 his duties changed and he reverted to the title of Program Officer supervising the Foundation's Urban Poverty program, a position he continued to hold after the division changed its name to Education and Public Policy in 1979. He retired from the Foundation on September 30, 1989. He died on May 20, 1994 at the age of 63.
Dorothy V. White worked in the Office of the Vice President of International Affairs as secretary to James Himes, the head of the Latin America and Caribbean Program. In that role she assisted with the preparation of grant recommendations and maintained correspondence files regarding the Foundation's educational grant-making.
Related Archival Collections
FA603 Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Education and Culture, Office Files of Peter W. Stanley, 1983-1992.
Peter Stanley was director of the Foundation's program in Education and Culture from 1984 to 1990. Education and Culture was a successor to Education and Public Policy and continued most of its responsibilities. This collection of office files includes papers from Edward J. Meade.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series.
Scope and Content Note
The Program Staff Files of the Higher Education and Research Division, spanning from 1954 to 1970, are an artificially created collection of documents assembled from the files of various staff members in the Higher Education and Research Division, International Affairs Division, and the Office of the Secretary.
An extensive set of files pertains to the Broadcasters Nonprofit Satellite Service (BNS). The Foundation developed a proposal in 1966 to establish BNS, a new nonprofit broadcasting association that would operate in the public interest in order to expand noncommercial educational television. The proposed service included creation of six commercial television channels and five noncommercial channels. AT&T and other broadcast networks opposed the proposal because it granted BNS a monopoly on satellite television broadcasting. Available in the files are the Federal Communication Commission filings by Ford, COMSAT, all three television networks, AT&T, and other involved parties such as Hughes Aircraft. The reports detail the proposed cost and function of the proposed satellite service, including technical information about satellite orbits and broadcast specifications. There are also meeting minutes and agenda concerning the Foundation proposal.
According to a March 1972 report to the trustees, the Paye-As-You-Earn (PAYE) project began in December 1970 as a Foundation Administered Project to study the financial, administrative, legal and public policy aspects of the income contingent loan. Income contingent loans obligate the borrower to pay a percentage of future annual income instead of a fixed payment schedule. The Foundation's interest in PAYE was inspired by Yale University's creation of a test program earlier in 1970. However, after a two year study and finding that the goal of more manageable student loans could better be achieved through a Federal government supported "graduated payment-income contingent" loan program, Foundation staff vetoed Foundation support for PAYE.
The PAYE files contain correspondence with a number of prominent universities that were considering or experimenting with PAYE loans. They also hold Board of Trustees meeting memoranda, notes, and correspondence regarding the Foundation's study. Issues considered in the study include alternatives such as payment over time, the specific application of PAYE loans to graduate schools of medicine and business, and the possible legal complications that could arise. The opinions of students were also sought as part of the review. Other memoranda describe supportive legislation proposed by several states, including New York, Indiana and Ohio. The files also contain a detailed Foundation study on variable-term loans.
The International files were created by Dorothy V. White, secretary to James R. Himes, the head of the Latin America and the Caribbean Program. The files reflect the overlap between the Education and International programs, as they refer to international grant-making by the Foundation for educational purposes. Topics include grant appropriations, grant recommendations, and discretionary project awards. Also covered in the files is the Foundation policy behind grant-making, including considerations about whether and how the Foundation should support business schools in India, and a guide for overseas development actions. In addition, there is information about internal office filing procedures and several reports on Foundation international grant-making.
The goal of the Foundation's Science and Engineering program, conducted under the direction of Dr. Carl Borgmann, was to increase the number of engineers and scientists in America in response to the Cold War threat posed by the Soviet Union. The program supported innovation in engineering curricula, including expanding the use of residency programs. The files in this collection provide background on the Foundation's science and engineering grant-making, from the development of the program in the mid-1950s to the decision to phase out the program and turn operation of the residency program over to the American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) in 1966. Several files in concern black educational institutions ("Negro Schools") and efforts to increase the number of African-American Engineers, and they detail the Foundation's grant-making at Fisk University. There is also a proposal for the establishment of the Southern Preparatory Center for Science and Engineering. The work with Negro Schools was a continuation of the Foundation's efforts to expand opportunities for American minority groups. Another file documents the Foundation's consideration and eventual rejection of astronomy as a field for philanthropic support.
Abel Amaya, Peter de Janosi, and Edward Meade Jr. were staff members within the Education Division. Dr. Amaya's files document his focus on Chicano education with universities. Dr. de Janosi's files cover a broader variety of topics as a result of his work as Officer in Charge of Higher Education. They include records of site visits, visits to European nations including Greece, Germany, Spain and Sweden, and documents related to the Conference on Foundation Programs in Europe and memoranda on. Dr. Meade's files focus on the educational issues of the 1960s including desegregation and support for disadvantaged minorities, studies on school drop-outs, and support for gifted youth and leadership programs.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Broadcasters Nonprofit Satellite Service (BNS), 1964-1967; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series, organized alphabetically by subject, contains Federal Communications Commission (FCC) filings, technical proposals, consultant reports, correspondence, and minutes and internal memoranda regarding the proposed implementation of the nonprofit service and the Foundation's proposal to the FCC.
  - ABC -- Submission to FCC, Dec 16, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Atmospheric and Orbital Charts, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - AT&T -- Submission to FCC -- Bell System Proposal, Dec 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Augustein, B. W. -- Comments on FF Proposal, Oct 6, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BNS III Write-Ups -- Satellite Description, Sep 9-Oct 5, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BNS Costs -- Tables, Write-Ups, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BNS Summary Contractual Report by Philco-Ford Corp (separated), Nov 7, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Carnegie Commission -- Correspondence Re: Educational TV, Report, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CBS -- Submission to FCC, Dec 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - COMSAT -- Submission to FCC, Aug 1, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Data on Networks, AT&T, General Systems and Finances (1 of 2), 1964-Sep 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Data on Networks, AT&T, General Systems and Finances (2 of 2), Oct 1966-Jan 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Educational TV (Educom) -- Costs, Feb-Apr 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Educational TV (ETV) -- Reports on Satellites and ITV (1 of 2), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Educational TV (ETV) -- Appropriations Request, PR Release, Background, etc. (2 of 2), 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ETV -- Federal Funds Distribution Report, [1966] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - FCC Supplemental Notice of Inquiry, Oct 21, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation -- Submission to FCC for Broadcasters' Nonprofit Satellite Service (BNS), Aug 1, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation -- Submission to FCC (1 of 3), Dec 12, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- Submission to FCC (2 of 3), Dec 12, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation -- Submission to FCC (3 of 3), Dec 12, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence -- Re: Satellite Systems, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hammett & Edison -- Consultancy Report, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hammett & Edison -- Satellite Traffic Usage Projections, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hughes Aircraft Company -- BNS Report (separated), Nov 7, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hughes Aircraft Company -- Correspondence Re: Contract, Oct-Nov 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Institute for Advanced Study -- Carl Kaysen Letter Re: Efficiency, Nov 18, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Johnson, Leland -- Papers on BNS, Review of FF Proposal, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Leland -- Visit to Aeronautical Radio, Inc. -- Report, Background, Nov 14, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Katz, Abraham -- Memo Re: Domestic Satellites, Information Outline, Sep 26, 1966-Feb 15, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Large Maps, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Levin, Harvey -- Paper on Broadcast Licenses and Case For Taxation, Oct 7, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agenda, Sep-Dec 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Scheduling Memos -- Howard Dressner, Aug-Sep 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Educational Television (NETV) -- Letter Re: NET, Oct 20, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - NBC -- Submission to FCC, Dec 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - NET -- Submission to FCC on FF Proposal, Dec 16, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pechman, Joseph -- Financing NET Memo, Nov 7, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Philco Corp -- Cost Study Correspondence, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Philco Corp -- Technical Proposal (1 of 2), Feb 14, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Philco Corp -- Technical Proposal (2 of 2), Feb 14, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pre-Ford Foundation Proposal Work Papers -- Paul MacAvoy Report, Hughes Aircraft Background, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Report on Commercial Underwriting in Educational Television", Dec 28, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Staff Memos on Economics of BNS, Aug-Sep 1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Status Reports, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Subcommittee Hearings on BNS -- Notes, Background Statements, Aug 1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Test Satellite Program -- Memos, Oct 1966 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Western Union -- Submission to FCC, Dec 1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- International Program, 1963-1970; II
  The files in this series are organized alphabetically by subject and include grant appropriations, grant recommendations, and discretionary project awards. There are also files on Foundation policy and filing procedures.
  - Appropriation Grant Recommendations (1 of 4), Jan 1969-Jan 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Appropriation Grant Recommendations (2 of 4), Feb-Mar 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Appropriation Grant Recommendations (3 of 4), Apr 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appropriation Grant Recommendations (4 of 4), May 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Discretionary Project Awards -- Summary Report and Evaluation, [1970] (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Filing -- Memoranda Re: FF Office Procedures, Grant Recommendations, etc., 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation International Programs -- Selected Question List -- 7th Annual Seminar for Advanced International Reporting Fellows from Columbia, Dec 12-13, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Office Building Press Fact Sheet, [1969] (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Grant Requests -- Asia and the Pacific (1 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Grant Requests -- Asia and the Pacific (2 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Grant Requests -- ID/Office of the Vice President (OVP) (1 of 2), 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Grant Requests -- ID/OVP (2 of 2), 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Guide For Overseas Development Actions, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - ITR -- Graduate Training and Research Grants 1951 to Date, Feb 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Management and Business Administration -- Memos and Reports Re: FF Support for Business Schools in India, etc., 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Report -- FF Annual Report, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Report -- FF Annual Report, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Report -- Planning for the Foundation's Activities in Europe, Dec 1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- PAYE (Pay-As-You-Earn), 1969-1972; III
  This series contains documents regarding the PAYE loan program. It includes both correspondence with universities considering or experimenting with PAYE loans, and Ford's own studies of the student loan issue. The files have been organized alphabetically by subject.
  - Antioch College -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Loans, Education Opportunity Bank, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bennington College -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: PAYE, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Background -- Harold Howe and Richard Brandenberg Memos, Feb-Jul 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Boston University -- Correspondence Re: Tuition Deferment Plan, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - California Institute of Technology -- Correspondence Re: Graduate Tuition Recovery, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Carleton College -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Proposal, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Consortium of Universities -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Loan Interviews, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Cornell University -- Correspondence Re: PAYE, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Duke University -- Correspondence, Memos, Notes Re: Tuition Deferment Plan, Site Visit, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Eastern Montana College -- Correspondence, Memos, Statement Re: PAYE, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Educational Investment Fund -- Cost Studies -- Correspondence, Background, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Educational Investment Fund Finance -- Correspondence, Memo Re: Fund Structure, etc., 1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Foreign Correspondence -- Re: Income Contingent Loans, May 1971 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Graduate Schools of Arts and Sciences -- Columbia, Princeton, Harvard -- Correspondence, Memo Re: Progress Reports, Meeting, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Graduate Schools of Business -- Correspondence Re: Student Survey, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Hampshire College -- Correspondence Re: PAYE Task Force, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - ICETEX -- Study Tour of Educational Loan Operations -- Itinerary, Jan 1972 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Illinois -- Memo Re: Government Official Visit, Notes, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Institutional Contacts -- Memos Re: Meetings, Notes, Lists, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Law Schools -- Memos Re: Financial Aid, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Legislation -- Indiana -- Memos Re: Proposed Law, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Legislation -- New York -- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Legislation -- Ohio -- Correspondence Re: Ohio Plan Incident, Newsclippings, Meeting Notes, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) -- Site Visit Memo Re: Income Contingent Lending, Jul 1971 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Medical Schools -- Preliminary Report, Correspondence, Notes, Comments, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - New Jersey -- Correspondence and Memos Re: Meetings on New Jersey Higher Education, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - PAYE -- Crane, Dwight -- Memos Re: Banker Information, Dec 1970 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - PAYE for Retraining and Disadvantaged -- Goal Programs, Nov 12-27, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - PAYE -- General Background -- Grant Action, Preliminary Statement, Memo Re: John Brademas Meeting, Jan 1971 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - PAYE Project Announcement Letter -- McGeorge Bundy, Dec 15, 1970-Jan 4, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - PAYE Project -- Bohen, Frederick -- Yale Meeting Background Notes and Memo Opposing Board Special Meeting, Jan 10, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - PAYE Project -- Carnegie Corporation of New York, Dec 17, 1970-Jan 4, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - PAYE Project -- Consortium of Grad Schools Meeting, Dec 7, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - PAYE Project -- FF Statement by Frederick Bohen, Jan 7, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - PAYE Project -- General Information -- FF Memos, Nov 23, 1970-Feb 26, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - PAYE Project -- Hausman, L. -- "Some Observations on PAYE", Jan 7, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - PAYE Project -- Kennedy, Roger -- Memos, Dec 17-23, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - PAYE Project -- Smith, Quentin -- Meeting Memo and Correspondence, Jan 7, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 23)